Désirée Grafton-Clarke

DEVELOPMENTAL PSYCHOLOGY AND LINGUISTICS RESEARCHER · PSYCHOPEDAGOGIST

245/6 Dalkeith Road, Edinburgh, Midlothian, EH16 5JS, UK

□ (+44) 7721891162 | **☑** graftond@tcd.ie | **☆** dezzygc.github.io | Enhanced DBS cert.no: 001572531588

Summary_

An ambitious and well-rounded early career researcher and psychopedagogist, with excellent teaching, pastoral and research skills. I am working towards a career in academic pedagogy, with interests in developmental psycholinguistics, childhood adversity and psychiatric neurobiology. My general research interests lie in **observational methods** in developmental psychology, theory of **psychometrics** and **experimental cognitive science**. I am particularly interested in the use of eye-tracking as a window to early language development in developmental disorders and the use of machine learning to advance psychometric and linguistic research. My other areas of interest relate to issues of promoting **accessibility and inclusion in further education**, particularly in relation to invisible disabilities, mature learners and under-represented socio-economic backgrounds.

Education

Trinity College Dublin, The University of Dublin

PhD in Developmental Psychology

- Thesis: Parent-Child Interaction and Neurodevelopmental Trajectories in Children with Down Syndrome
- Supervisors: Dr Jean Quigley, Dr Elizabeth Nixon
- Additional CPD Credited Modules Attended: Conducting Research in Psychology (PS7130), Regression, Adapting our Teaching for Learning Online (VP10021, Teaching and Supporting Learning as a Graduate Teaching Assistant (VP1017)

Newcastle University

BSc Hons Psychology, upper 2.1

- Thesis: The Effect of Childhood Adversity on the Onset of Infantile Amnesia
- Supervisors: Dr Sinead Mullally, Institute of Neuroscience
- courses included: The Psychology of Teaching & Learning (1st), Forensic Psychology,
 Developmental Disorders, Clinical Psychology, Eating Disorders, Advanced Developmental Psychology

Teaching _____

Disability Service Education Support Worker

MATHEMATICS, STATISTICS AND COMPUTATION (MAU11002)

- · Academic tutor for BSc Human Health and Disease (Junior Fresh) Calculus and Statistics module
- Provided 1:1 academic support for a student with vision impairment
- · Assisted with educational tasks, including revision of course material (practical work and theory)
- Developed familiarity with student assistive technologies e.g. Jaws, Zoomtext

Disability Service Education Support Worker

RESEARCH METHODS FOR POLITICAL SCIENCE A

- 1:1 educational support for 3rd year Political Science student with Dyslexia
- Provided tutorials on quantitative research methods
- Cultivated student understanding and confidence in using statistical software R studio
- Equipped student with strategies for preparation of assignments and exams

Disability Service Education Support Worker

RESEARCH METHODS FOR POLITICAL SCIENCE B

- 1:1 academic support for 3rd year Political Science student with Dyslexia
- 1:1 academic support for 3rd year Philosophy, Political Science, Economics and Sociology (PPES) student with a mental health condition
- Provided supplementary practical tutorials on quantitative statistics using R
- Supported consolidation of module material in preparation for summative assessment

Teaching Assistant

RESEARCH SKILLS AND METHODOLOGY I, STATISTICS AND METHODOLOGY II

- Demonstrator for first year (Single Honors and Postgraduate Conversion Course) practical statistics labs
- Taught quantitative statistical analyses in statistical software SPSS (2018-2020) and more recently, in Python via Google Collaboratory (2020/21)
- · Additional responsibilities included grading student assignments and providing feedback on lab reports
- Experienced in delivering module content face-to-face and online via Zoom

Dublin, Republic of Ireland

Sept. 2017 - August. 2021

Newcastle Upon Tyne, UK

Sep. 2013 - June. 2016

Disability Service, MAU11002

October 2020 - August 2021

Disability Service, POU33011

October 2020 - June 2021

Disability Service, POU33012

January 2020 - June 2021

School of Psychology, PSU1010/1

September 2018 - June 2021

ADVANCED THEORETICAL ISSUES

- Delivered seminars for Senior Sophister Psychology Students
- Mediated and facilitated in-class academic debates
- Liaised with academic staff to inform topics of seminars, including Psychology of Language, Neuroscience, Individual Differences, Neuroethics, Social Psychology, Moral Reasoning and Principles of Open Science
- Assisted students' preparation of summative essays

Tutorial Lead School of Psychology, PSU11005

ACADEMIC SKILLS TUTORIALS

- · Delivered tutorials for groups of Junior Fresh Psychology Students on academic reading and writing skills
- · Designed tutorial curriculum and tailored essay titles according to evolving interests of students and own expertise
- · Responsible for assessment administration and grading
- · Guided students in their development of key academic skills, including critical thinking, essay writing and referencing

Personal Module Instructor

School of Psychology, PSU33013

November 2019 - June 2020

September 2017 - June 2021

September 2018 - January 2021

PRACTICALS, METHODOLOGY AND STATS III

- Responsible for delivering all module content 1:1 for a Junior Sophister student who is Hard of Hearing and experiencing extenuating circumstances
- Liaised with the Undergraduate Director of Teaching and Learning and the Disability Support Service in supporting student progress, reasonable accommodations and pastoral support
- · Provided tutorials and practicals in quantitative research methods, including statistical analysis using Python
- · Attended training sessions with student to fulfill an additional scribing role at their summative exams

Academic SupportTrinity Access ProgramVARIOUSApril 2019 - June 2020

- Provided ad-hoc academic support via 1:1 tutorials for students from under-represented socio-economic backgrounds via Trinity's Access Program
- Ad hoc academic support for mature students in the Psychology Postgraduate Conversion Course
- Modules included Personality and Individual Differences, Evolutionary Psychology and Statistics
- Supported students in preparation for deferred exams and/or resits

Publications _

Growing up unloved: the enduring consequence of early emotional neglect on the qualia of memory and imagination

submitted for peer review

S MULLALLY, D GRAFTON-CLARKE, E MAWSON, M UNWIN, M STAPLETON, K WEBBER, K ROSSI, S BROWN, A DODD, D COKAL, P GALLAGHER AND S WATSON

Selected Research Presentations

We need to talk! Insights from Mothers' and Fathers' speech to their children with Down Syndrome - Oral Presentation

Online Conference

DOWN SYNDROME EDUCATION INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH FORUM 2021

Mar. 2021

• D.F Grafton-Clarke, L. Kelly, E. Nixon, and J. Quigley

The Power of Parents: Understanding the Significance of Parent-Child Interaction for Child Development in Down Syndrome - Oral Presentation

University College London, UK

Down Syndrome Education International Research Forum 2019

Sep. 2019

• D Grafton-Clarke, E Nixon, E Molloy and J Quigley

Use of Mental State Terms by Mothers of Children with Down Syndrome and Child Expressive Language Ability - Poster Presentation

Held Online

THE 6TH LANCASTER CONFERENCE ON INFANT AND EARLY CHILD DEVELOPMENT

Aug. 2021

- A Owens, D Grafton-Clarke, J Quigley, E Nixon
- Final year project student
- Final year project student

Maternal Verbal Directives to Toddlers with Down Syndrome: Evidence for Maternal Attunement to Child Language - Poster Presentation

Held Online

THE 6TH LANCASTER CONFERENCE ON INFANT AND EARLY CHILD DEVELOPMENT

Aug. 2021

- I Macaulay, D Grafton-Clarke, E Nixon, J Quigley
- Final year project student

JULY 5, 2021 D F GRAFTON-CLARKE · CV

Don't BabyTalk me! Are Parents Oversimplifying Language to Children with Down Syndrome? - Lightbulb Presentation

CHILDREN'S RESEARCH NETWORK 2019 CONFERENCE

• D Grafton-Clarke, E Nixon, E Molloy and J Quigley

The Relationship between Reported Childhood Adversity and Adult Hippocampus Function - Poster Presentation

Brighton, UK

BRITISH ASSOCIATION FOR PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY SUMMER MEETING 2016

Grafton-Clarke DF, Kotha R, Thompson S, Mullally SL, Harrison and Watson S

Jul 2016

Nov. 2019

Skills

Statistical Software SPSS Statistics, GSEQ (Generalized Sequential Querier), Minitab

Programming Python, R, MATLAB

Linguistics Software CLAN, ELAN, F4 Transkript, Praat, Boris, Mangold INTERACT **AV and technical software** Mangold VideoSyncPro, SR Research EyeLink, SR DataViewer

Standardized Assessments Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale, Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children, Bayley Scales of Infant

Development, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale, The Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5,

Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence

Assistive Technologies ZoomText, Jaws, Dragon, MindGenius

Languages and Manual Sign English, Lámh Communication Augmentation Sign System

Video and Audio Editing Adobe PremierePro, Adobe Audition, Adobe Lightroom, NCH VideoPad,

Adobe WavePad, NCH MixPad, Audacity

Research Experience_

Section Editor (Psychiatry and Mental Health)

NSAMRJ

NATIONAL STUDENT ASSOCIATION OF MEDICAL RESEARCH JOURNAL

October 2016 - 2018

- · Volunteer Section editor for NSAMRJ, a biannual peer-reviewed journal funded by the Wellcome Trust
- Liased with peer reviewers to co-ordinate reviews before a specified deadline
- · Compiled comments into reports and advised executive editorial team on article acceptance or non-acceptance
- Rated peer reviewers against set criteria
- · Peer-reviewed article submissions

'The Language and Mental Health Project' - Research Assistant

Wolfson Research Centre

Academic Psychiatry and Regional Affective Disorders Service, Newcastle-Upon-Tyne

May 2015 - June 2017

- Conducted linguistic analyses on speech recordings from a non-clinical cohort of individuals with varied history
 of childhood adversity
- Transcribed & analysed linguistic features of speech
- Prepared submissions for publication and presentation

'The Childhood Trauma Study' - Research Assistant

Newcastle University
May 2015 - June 2017

INSTITUTE OF NEUROSCIENCE

 Cross-disciplinary project investigating the mechanism underlying the relationship between childhood adversity and mood disorders, with specific reference to the impact on hippocampal function and language

• Analysed and disseminated findings, including preparation of submissions for conferences and publication

'Auditory Sequence Analysis and Language Skill in Adolescents' - Research Assistant

Newcastle University

THE AUDITORY GROUP, INSTITUTE OF NEUROSCIENCE

September 2015 - March 2016

- Received formal training in standardized intelligence assessments
- Administered the WAIS, WISC and an auditory attention task with year 7 students at a secondary school
- Scored, recorded and interpretted assessments

Affiliations & Awards_

2021 Member, International Congress of Infant Studies

2018 Member, Children's Research Network

2016 **Graduate Member, MBPsS**, British Psychological Society

2016 **Trainee Member**, British Association of Psychopharmacology

2013 Bronze, Silver and Gold, Duke of Edinburgh Award

2005 **MENSA**, Member and Psychology SIG

Extracurricular and Voluntary Roles

Student Ambassador Trinity College Dublin

STUDENT DISABILITY SUPPORT SERVICE

2018 - 2021

- Postgraduate Research Representative for Disability Support Service
- Provided information about the Disability Service in presentations to prospective students, parents and incoming students at orientation events and open days
- Engaged in Ambassador Training and Leadership Program
- Provided details about courses in Trinity and information about the disability service at partner schools for Senior
 Cycle students, including information relating to the Higher Education Access Route (HEAR) and Disability Access Route (DARE)

Listening Volunteer Newcastle University

NSU NIGHTLINE

• Volunteer for a confidential and anonymous listening and information service for students

- · Attended training on active listening and communication skills for responding to students experiencing distress
- Duties involved answering calls or messages from students during the night

St John Ambulance various

ADVANCED FIRST AIDER 2012 - 2019

- · Attended weekly First Aid training and annual renewal exams
- Volunteered regularly as an event First Aider at public events
- · Certified in adult and paediatric resuscitation and AED

Hack NE - 24 hour programming event

Major League Hacking (MLH)

October 2015 - June 2016

November 2014

- Assisted with organizing the largest coding Hackathon in the North East (Link Here)
- In cooperation with Major League hacking and sponsors:
 Bede Gaming, Bloomberg, PayPal, Braintree, SendGrid, Capital One and namecheap

References_

HACKATHON ASSIST

To Be Provided Upon Request